# 福建·泉州
(Quanzhou, Fujian)
# 我们今天要去尝尝这个
Today we are going to try this hand-made maci (rice cake)
# 地方不大
small place though
# 堂食请自取
Please self-serve in the cafeteria
# 额 糟糕
oh blast
# 每当看菜单的时候 我都会变的很纠结
Whenever I see the menu, I get anxious
# 因为你不知道 应该点哪一种
because you don't know which one should you order
# 还有 一个或一份的量 到底有多大
And also, you don't know how big one order or one portion is
# 让我开心的是 这次没有
but to my great joy, not this time
# （图片仅供参考）
photo for reference only
# 三个（古早味）手工麻糍 三个花生馅的
three (traditional nostalgic style) hand made maci, 3 with peanut stuffing
# 再要一个冷冰
and one shaved ice
# 你稍等一下
OK, please wait a sec
# 哦可以
OK
# 三个这个花生
three with peanut stuffing
# 三个古早
three traditional ones, 6 in total
# 现在要不要先吃古早味的 要的话 我就先包给你们
do you wish to start with the traditional ones? If so I'll make them first
# 然后再帮你做冰
then prepare the shaved ice
# 就是古早味没办法达到那么长时间
since the traditional ones can not hold that long
# 哦 明白 行 可以
Ok I understand, ok sure
# 那就先做这个 就先吃它
Then first make this one, I'll eat it first
# 可以 可以
Ok, ok.
# 哦 这个是不能够放时间很长的
Oh, so the traditional ones don't hold long, right?
# 不能放长时间的
Can't leave it out for too long
# 为什么
why?
# 你吃几口就知道了 不会脆的
Have a bite and you'll understand (it will become less crispy)
# 呃不会脆的
Oh, it won't be crispy
# 花生的 没关系
Ones with peanut stuffing don't have this problem
# 花生的晚一点没关系
Peanut ones will be fine even if you wait a bit
# 可以
Sure
# 来
here you are
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 然后呢 你们可以上楼坐
So... you can seat yourself upstairs
# 行 我先付钱吧 (等一下我再帮你们把冰拿上去)
Ok, let me pay first.
(I'll bring the shaved ice upstairs in a bit)
# 可以 可以 好 谢谢
Ok, Ok, sure, thank you.
# (糖粉) 12+12=24
(Powdered sugar)
12 plus 12 equals 24 (yuan)
# 我先上去吃这个吧
I'll go upstairs and eat this first
# 好 谢谢 麻烦了 (花生馅)
Sure, thank you for your trouble!
(peanut stuffing)
# 黄豆面
roasted soybean powder
# 楼梯这么窄
the stairs are quite narrow
# 我手上的就是古早味的手工麻糍 古早味的手工麻糍
So what I have in my hand is a traditional nostalgic style hand-made maci
# （这家店做的）是这种梭形的
(The ones from this store) are in the shape of a spindle
# 从我刚进来 到现在拿到手工麻糍
from the moment I arrived, until now where I have the maci in my hand
# 围绕在我周围的 全部都是黄豆粉的这种香味
I have been completely enveloped by the aromatic fragrance of roasted soybean powder
# 它这个是拿麻糍面团
it is made with glutinous rice dough
# 把它扯成一个稍微圆的饼的形状
Hand pulled into a sort of round biscuit shape
# 然后包上这个
And then stuffed with this
# 有点类似薄脆吧
Something flaky-ish
# 炸的薄薄的 脆脆的
Fried thin and crispy
# 这种小的油炸的东西
These smaller, deep fried things
# 把它包进去 然后丢到黄豆粉里
Stuff it, then toss it in the soybean flour
# 团一团 就成了这个手工麻糍
Roll it around, and you'll have this hand-made maci
# 谢谢
Thanks
# 上面这一粒粒是热的 热的
These bits on the top are hot (Hot?)
# 对 你要挖一个和冰一起吃
you can eat the hot bits at the same time with the ice
# 对 这个跟冰
Yes, this one with ice
# 再加一点冰 再挖一点冰 下面是冰 对
Add some ice, dig a little deeper, ice is on the bottom. Yep.
# 这个是什么呀, 这个热的
What's this, the hot thing?
# 这是阿达子 阿达子
Adazi (tapioca cube)
(made from tapioca starch, often found in "yu yuans")
# 就是它下面还有芋头那些
you can also find taro underneath
# 芋泥是吧
you mean taro puree?
# 不 不 不 我们是芋头 芋头
No no no, we use actual taro chunks, taro chunks.
# 对 对 对 谢谢
cool, thanks
# 等一下下楼要慢一点
be careful when you go downstairs
# 感觉好温暖
It feels so cozy
# 哇 阿达子是热的 但是冰是凉的 两个就是冰火两重天
Wow, the adazi is warm, but the shaved ice is cold, combined it's like a fire and ice explosion
# 但同时都在嘴里
Simultaneously in your mouth
# 这阿达子有点这种QQ糖的口感
Adazi has a texture similar to gummy candy
# 刚才这个小姐姐说 下面是有芋头的
The lady mentioned that there's taro underneath
# 看我把冰山挖过来 能不能看到芋头
Watch me dig up this iceberg, and see if we can find the taro
# 我真的是来到泉州之后觉得 这边有很多做芋头的小吃
Ever since I arrived in Quanzhou, i found there are so many snacks made of taro
# 把它做成甜品 (热Q冷冰: 上面是阿达子 花生碎, 下面有冰, 西米露, 芋头)
Used for desserts
(Hot Q Shaved ice: on top is adazi, crushed peanuts, underneath is ice, sago, taro)
# 但是 芋头又不会做的特别甜
But the taro is not overly sweetened
# 这应该是芋头吧
This should be the taro, right?
# 它这个糯米糍是糯米做的
The glutinous rice cake is made of glutinous rice
# 外面细腻 软糯
Soft yet firm on the outside
# 但是里面包的这种薄脆 油炸的东西
But inside stuffed with these lightly flaky, fried things
# 吃起来又是这种香脆感
And with a unique satisfyingly crispy texture
# 两个是完全不同的口味
Two entirely different experiences
# 但是同时都会在你的口中 发生这种物理反应
reacting harmoniously in your mouth
# 最开始怎么会想到做手工麻糍的呢
How did you come up with this idea of making maci?
# 这个其实是漳州的小吃 漳州的
This is actually a specialty of Zhangzhou. (Zhangzhou?)
# 对 因为我去那边吃到 我好几年前
Yes, because I ate it over there... many years ago
# 第一次吃的感觉 哇 好好吃
My first impression was "Wow! It's so delicious!"
# 但是没有什么想法 因为那时候我在上班
But I did not give too much thought into it because I was working at the time.
# 后面再去吃
Later on I went to eat it again
# 因为跟我女儿在讲的时候 我们讲到漳州 就会想到它嘛
Because when talking to my daughter, as soon as we talk about Zhangzhou, we'd think about the maci.
# 后面再去吃的时候 就突然 想说 泉州没有 所以就引进过来了
so when i went there to eat it again, we were saying: well we don't have it in Quanzhou, so we introduced it to Quanzhou
# 关 注 雪 鱼 探 店
(Subscribe)